嘿，你们好，我是TheCherno，欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno, welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么我们上次说了纹理
so last time we talked about textures
具体来说，我们把TheChernoLogo图片渲染到屏幕上的一个四边形上
and specifically we got TheChernoLogo rendering onto a quad essentially on our screen
所以如果你们还没看过那期视频，一定要去点开看看
so if you haven't seen that video, definitely click up there and watch it
它对于今天还是比较重要的
it's gonna be important for today
因为在上一期的最后
because at the very end of that episode last time
我们在渲染纹理时遇到了一些问题
we had a bit of an issue with how our texture was actually rendering
而不是留给你们一个悬念
and then instead of leaving you guys with a cliff hanger
我真的很想这么做
which I was very attempted to actually do
但是没有，所以我还是比较好的，对吧
but didn't, so yeah it was nice for me, right
我们实际上讲了一点混合
we actually talked a little bit about blending
特别地，我们启用了一个叫做混合的东西，我们设置了一个混合函数
and specifically we enabled something called blending, and we set a blend function
这就随机得到了我们的纹理
and that got our texture and randomly
那么如果我们看一下代码，特别是我们加了这两行代码
so if we take a look at the code, specifically we added these two lines
如果我把它们注释掉并运行我的程序
if I comment them out and run my program
我们会得到一个奇怪的纹理
we will get a weird looking texture
所以这就是我们的纹理，看起来很奇怪
so there's our texture, looks pretty weird
如果我回到我的代码，我只启用第一行
if I go back to my code, and I just enable this first line
这个是首先启用混合的
which is just enabling blending in the first place
看起来完全一样
it looks well exactly the same
如果我启用这两行代码
and if I enable both of these lines
然后我们得到一些看起来更正常的东西
then we get something that looks a little bit more normal
或者是我们所期望的
or something that we would expect which is well
这与源图像非常相似
this which is really resembling the source image
在这个例子中，我们实际上用它作为纹理
that we actually used as a texture in this case
所以我很快地跳过了这两行，我并没有真正地解释它们
so I quickly out of those two lines, and I didn't really explain them
因为我想把它们留到这个视频中
because I wanted to save them for this video
这将解释什么是混合
which is going to be explaining what blending actually is
今天我甚至做了一些不同的事情
and I've even done something a little bit different today
我希望你们在接下来的视频中会喜欢
which I hope you'll enjoy in the rest of this video
好了，那么混合，它是什么
okay, so blending, what is it
为什么我们的纹理渲染在一开始就不正确
and why was our texture rendering incorrectly in the first place
那么混合很简单的
so blending is pretty simple
本质上，当我们渲染一些部分或完全透明的东西时
it's essentially, when we render something that is partially or fully transparent
我们该怎么做，对吧
how do we do that, right
如果我有一些透明的概念
if I have something with a concept of transparency
首先，你们必须意识到，对你们和我来说
first of all, you have to realize that, to you and me
当我们谈到透明度的时候
when we talk about transparency
我们会想到PS
and we think of something maybe like in photoshop
当你们降低一个图层的不透明度
when you turn down the opacity of a layer
或者你们有像玻璃这样的东西，你们要渲染
or you have something like glass that you're rendering
就像这样
that is like kind of there
但实际上并不是大部分都是由反射组成的
but not really mostly made up of reflections perhaps
或者它是有色玻璃，所以它倾向可视化某种颜色
or maybe it's colored glass, so it kind of tends to view a certain color
这对我们的大脑来说是有意义的
it all kind of makes sense to us in our brain
我们说，是的，这就是我想要的，对吧
and we're like, yeah, that's what I expect to happen, right
但当我们谈到图形编程时
but when we're talking about graphics programming
你们必须告诉电脑你真正想让它做什么
you have to tell the computer what you actually want it to do
因为它不知道你们想做什么
because it doesn't know what you want to do
默认情况下，OpenGL不执行任何混合
and by default, OpenGL doesn't perform any kind of blending
它只需要你们渲染的东西
it just kind of takes whatever you're rendering
然后把它渲染成不透明的东西
and just renders it as if it was just something opaque
或者一些正常的东西，或者和它很正常的东西，对吧
or something normal, or something well normal to it, right
所以只要记住，当我们讨论这些概念
so just keep in mind that, when we talk about all these kind of concepts
你们所期望的并不一定是计算机所期望的
what you expect is not necessarily what the computer expects
你们可能有不同的定义
and you may have different definitions
所以这就是为什么我们要回到基础上来
so that's why we're going to go back to basics
我甚至还准备了一个ppt演示
and I've even prepared a bit of a powerpoint presentation
我觉得我以前从没做过这种事
which is something that I don't think I've ever done before
所以请告诉我你们对这种风格的看法
so let me know what you think of this kind of style
因为我真的很想用一些图表来解释
because I really wanted to kind of have some diagrams to explain
什么是混合，那么什么是混合
what blending actually was, so what is blending
所以我想我们有了这个我们渲染过的红色方块
so I suppose that we had this red square that we rendered and
在它上面，我们以某种形式渲染了一个蓝色的正方形
on top of it in some form, we rendered a blue square
现在这个例子中的蓝色方块是半透明的，对吧
now this blue square in this example is going to be partially translucent, right
它不会是一个完全不透明的蓝色方块
it's not going to be a fully opaque blue square
因为如果我们把它渲染在红色方块的上面
because if we just rendered that on top of our red square
我们根本看不到红色方块，我们会得到一个蓝色的正方形
well we wouldn't see the red square at all, we would just get a blue square
但是在这个例子中
however in this example
假设这个蓝色的正方形真的像一片蓝色的玻璃
pretend that this blue square is really like a sheet of blue glass
或者类似的东西
or something like that
我们期望得到这两种颜色的组合
we would expect to get a combination of those two colors
我们认为是紫色的，对吧
which we would perceive as purple, right
如果我们在现实生活中拿红玻璃和蓝玻璃
if we literally in real life took red glass and blue glass
然后把它们像这样叠在一起
and then put them on top of each other like this
我们会看到穿过的光实际上是紫色的
we would see light coming through would actually be tented purple
那就是我们用眼睛所看到的
and that's what we would perceive with our eyes
更具体地说，如果我们看看这是什么样子
more specifically, if we actually look at what this looks like
如果我们渲染一个红色的正方形，然后在它上面渲染一个蓝色的正方形
if we rendered a red square, and then a blue square on top of it
但蓝色正方形实际上是半透明的
but the blue square was in fact translucent
我们会看到这样的东西
we would see something like this
这就是两种颜色的组合
which is the combination of those two colors
所以混合只是决定了
so blending just determines
我们如何将输出颜色与目标缓冲区中已经存在的颜色结合起来
how we actually combine our output color with what is already in our target buffer
那么什么是我们的输出颜色
so what is our output color
那是我们从片段着色器中输出的颜色，也被称为source(来源)
that's the color that we output from our fragmente shader, and known as source
所以在这个例子中，我们输出的是蓝色
so in this case, we're outputting a blue color
因为我们渲染的是一个蓝色的正方形
because we're rendering a blue square
然后目标缓冲区就是我们画蓝色方块的地方
and then the target buffer is where we're actually drawing that blue square onto
那么，在这个例子中，我们把它画到一个已经存在的缓冲区上
so in this case, we're drawing it onto an already existing buffer
也就是我们的destination(目标)，在这个例子中包含一个红色方块
known as our destination, which in this case contains a red square
那么我们如何控制这两种颜色混合的方式
so how do we actually control the way that these two colors get blended
我们在OpenGL中有三种不同的方法，它们做的事情非常不同
well we really have three different ways in OpenGL, and they do very different things
那么首先，启用和禁用，就是glEnable和glDisable，参数GL_BLEND
so first of all, enable and disable, glEnable and disable blend
首先启用和禁用混合
enable and disable blending in the first place
如果你们没有启用混合，默认情况下是不会启用的
if you don't have blending enabled, which you won't by default
那么什么都不会发生
then nothing is going to happen
它完全不会混合
your it's just not gonna blend at all
所以你们要做的第一件事
so the first thing you need to do
这也是我们在代码中做的第一件事
which is also the first thing that we did in our code
就是glEnable(GL_BLEND)
was glEnable GL_BLEND
其次，我们有一个叫glBlendFunc的函数
secondly, we have something called glBlendFunc
它接收一个src和dest参数
which takes a src and a dest
我们调用的这个函数基本上指定了
and this function that we call basically specifies
我们如何将这两种颜色混合在一起
how we actually blend the two colors together
那么src就是src的RGBA因子的计算方式
so the src is how the src RGBA factor is computed
默认为GL_ONE
by default, this is GL_ONE
dest就是计算dest的RGBA因子的方式，默认值是GL_ZERO
dest is how the dest RGBA factor is computed, by default, this is zero
所以这就清楚多了
so this is going to be all a lot clearer
我马上就会深入讲解这些例子
when I actually dive into examples in a minute
但当我谈到src的RGBA因子时
but when I talk about the src RGBA factor essentially
这个混合函数决定了我们要做什么
what this blend function determines is what we do
当我们执行混合等式时
when we perform our blending equation is
我们取src和dest的RGBA的每个颜色通道
we take each color channel of the src RGBA and the dest RGBA
不一定是RGBA，也可以是RGB
doesn't have to be RGBA, can just be RGB
或者你们使用的任何颜色格式
or whatever color format you are using
但是每一个颜色通道，我们都取实际值
but every color channel, we take that actual value
然后用它乘以某个数
and we multiply it with something
然后乘以的这个东西就是我们指定的这个RGBA因子
and this something that we multiply it with is this RGBA factor that we specify
所以当我们看到默认是GL_ONE
so when we see that the default is GL_ONE
那意味着我们实际上取src的RGBA所有通道或单独取
that means we literally take our src RGBA channels or separately
然后乘以1，任何数乘以1
and we multiply them with 1, now anything multiplied with 1
也就是x乘以1等于x，对吧
x multiplied by 1 is going to be x, right
所以换句话说，无论src是什么，它都不会改变
so in other words, whatever the src is, that does not change
至于dest，但是我们知道默认情况下它被设为0
the dest, however we know that we by default it's set to zero
任何数乘以0都是0
and anything multiplied with zero is zero
所以这基本上是在说
so what this is basically saying
这个默认的glGenBlendFunc会丢掉dest，用src覆盖它，对吧
this default glGenBlendFunc is throw away the dest, and just override it with the src, right
因为src中的所有东西都乘以1，这意味着它不会改变
because everything in the src gets multiplied with one, which means it doesn't change
dest中的所有东西都乘以0
and everything in the dest gets multiplied with zero
这意味着它没了，对吧，变成了零
which means that it just gets nuked, right, it becomes zero
所以我们有两个独立的东西，对吧
so we have those two separate things, right
src是不变的，dest被设置为零
the src is just unchange, and the dest has been set to zero
现在我们需要对这两个分量做点什么
and now we need to do something with these two components that we have
这就来到了第三步
and that's where this third thing comes in
这就是我们的混合等式(glBlendEquation)
which is called our blending equation
所以mode基本上是指定
so the mode basically just specifies
作为这个函数文本指定的一个参数，我们如何组合src和dest颜色
as the one parameter that this function texts specifies, how we combine the src and dest colors
但默认是增加(GL_FUNC_ADD)
but default it's add
那么我们有我说过的这两种颜色
so we had those two colors that I said
我们有了src和dest，我们需要对这两个分量做些什么
we had the src and the dest, we need to do something with those two components
我们把它们加起来，增加的意思就是加
we add them together by add it just means plus
对吧，你们取src的任何颜色也就是src的颜色乘以1
right, so you take whatever the src color is which was the src color multiplied with 1
所以也就是src颜色
so just the src color
然后再加上，dest的颜色乘以0，也就是0
and then you add to it, the dest color multiplied by zero which is zero
所以我们就取src，加上0等于src
so we take src, and we add zero to it which equals src
所以在这个例子中，默认情况下，我们会得到一些东西
so in this example by default, we get something
这本质上是1加0，也就是1
this is essentially one plus zero which is just one
对吧，这意味着使用src值
right, which this means use the src value
这并不意味着仅是src的alpha值，我指的是所有的颜色通道
now this does not mean the src alpha value, I literally mean all of the color channels
不管src是什么，就用那个src颜色覆盖dest
just take whatever the src is, and override the dest with that src color
那是在OpenGL中发生的
that is what happens in OpenGL
默认情况下，如果你们不设置混合函数
by default, if you don't set a blend function
然而，我们所做的是使用一些东西
however what we did is we used something
实际上，我们专门设置了一个混合函数
we actually set a blend function as specifically
使用的src是GL_SRC_ALPHA, dest是GL_ONE_MINUS_SRC_ALPHA
we used the src being GL_SRC_ALPHA, and dest being GL_ONE_MINUS_SRC_ALPHA
这个导致了那个结果
which is what got us that result
这和我们预期的很像
that looked like something that we would expect
那么举个简单的例子
so to show a simple example
使用我们在这里设置的src和dest函数值
using these src and dest function values that we actually set here
如果我们从纹理中输入的像素是完全透明的，对吧
if the pixel that we're entering from our texture is completely transparent, right
所以我的意思是alpha值被设为0，它是完全透明的
so what I mean by that is the alpha is set to 0, it's completely transparent
src alpha= 0，dest = 1 - src alpha(0)
our src alpha is 0, our dest is 1 minus src alpha
所以你们可以看到这里，我们把src设置为GL_SRC_ALPHA
so you can see over here, we've set our src to be GL_SRC_ALPHA
这意味着不管使用这些src的alpha值是什么
which means use whatever these src alpha value is
因为它是透明的，它都是0
since it's transparent, is 0
dest要求减去src的alpha
the dest says take the minus of that src alpha
那么我们看一下src是0
so we look at the src alpha which is 0
我们用1减去src的alpha
and we do 1 minus the src alpha
也就是说，1 - 0 =1，因为src是0，那么我们有这两个值
so in other words, 1 minus 0, since our src alpha is 0, equals 1, so we have those two values
现在我们该怎么处理它们
and now what do we do with them
如果我们看一下这后面的等式
well if we look at the actual equation behind this
它实际上只是指使用目标颜色，该颜色已经在缓冲区中
it is actually just means use the destination color, the color is already in the buffer
因为alpha通道是0表示它是透明的，也就是说我们看不到它
because alpha 0 means it's transparent, which means we don't see it
所以我们根本不应该写一个像素
so we shouldn't really be writing a pixel at all
只需使用目标缓冲区中像素后面的任何值
just use whatever values behind that pixel in that destination buffer
我们看看这后面的映射，你可以看到每个通道
we actually look at the maps behind this, you can see that for each channel
让我们假设我们有一个RGBA纹理和RGBA缓冲
let's just pretend we have an RGBA texture and RGBA buffer
我们取Rsrc，乘以src的alpha，也就是0
we take the src red channel, we multiplied by the src alpha, which is 0
然后我们再加上
and then we add to it
Rdest*(1-0)
the dest red channel multiplied by the minus of that
所以在这个例子中乘以1
so multiplied by 1 in this case
当然，0加上dest值，就得到了dest值
and of course, 0 plus whatever the dest value is, gives us the dest value
我们对每一个颜色通道都这样做
and we do that for every single color channel
所以你们可以看到这个掩码是可行的
so you can see that this mask kind of works out
这样我们就不用任何src颜色了
so that we just don't use any of the src color at all
我们只在实际的缓冲区中保留dest颜色
we just keep the dest color in the actual buffer
我们根本不会影响缓冲区
we don't affect the buffer at all
让我们看一个稍微复杂一点的例子
let's look at a slightly more complicated example
因为那个很简单
because that was really simple
那么假设我们的像素是部分透明的
so pretend that our pixel is partially transparent here
让我们看看我们有这种白色方块
let's just see that we've got this kind of white square
它是半透明的，对吧
that is translucent, right
它的RGB是111，但alpha是0.5
it's got an RGB of 1 1 1, but the alpha is 0.5
那么这里，我们有一个白色方块
so here it is, we've got a white square
它是白色的，但却是半透明的
it's white, but it's translucent
然后在我们的目标缓冲区中，我们有这种类型的目标缓冲区
and then in our destination buffer, we've just got this kind of destination buffer
我们已经把它清除成洋红色了，也就是(1, 0, 1)，把alpha也保存为1
which we've just cleared to magenta, so 1 0 1, and we'll save the alpha as one as well
就这儿，好了
here it is, okay
所以使用我们当前的混合设置src的alpha，以及1减去src的alpha
so using our current bleneing settings of src alpha, and 1 minus src alpha
我们来看看这块，红色通道是1，对吧
let's take a look at the mass, so the red channel is 1, right
因为src的红色通道在这里是1，这是我们的白色方块
because the src red channel is 1 over here, it's our white square
我们用这个乘以src的alpha，也就是0.5
we multiply that with these src alpha which is 0.5
然后我们加上dest红色通道，也就是1
and then to that we add the dest red channel which is 1
乘以1减去src的alpha
multiplied by the minus of that src alpha 1
src的alpha是0.5
src alpha which is 0.5
结果是0.5，再加上0.5就是1
and then that works out to be 0.5, plus 0.5 wishes just 1
所以换句话说，我们在渲染1
so in other words, we're rendering 1
对于很多通道来说都是这样的
now this is going to be the case for a lot of these channels
因为你们可以看到
because you can see that
我们在每个地方都渲染一个，而不是0.7之类的
we're literally rendering ones everywhere not like 0.7 or something
我们确实处于非本地颜色范围内的粉红色
we're literally at the kind of pink of our non here color range
绿色通道也有点像这样
so the green channel is also going to be a little bit like this
但是你们可以看到目标绿色通道是0
but you can see that our green channel for our destination is just 0
但是，由于我们的源的绿色通道是1
however since the green channel for our src is 1
我们把它们混合在一起，让它变成一半，结果是0.5
we basically blend that together and made it halfway, and it gives us 0.5
蓝色通道是相同的，alpha通道稍微改变了一点
blue channel is going to be identical, alpha channel changes a little bit
因为0.5和它的一半相加，得到0.75
because we're combining 0.5 and one halfway between that we get 0.75
如果我们要把这个白色方块渲染到这个洋红色矩形的上面
so if we were to render this white square on top of this magenta rectangle
我们会得到看起来像那样的结果
we would get something that looks like that
如果我取这些颜色值，然后渲染它们
if I just take these color values and I render them
这就是我得到的，这就是你们所期望的
that's what I get, and that's kind of what you would expect
如果你们有一个白色的方块，像白色的玻璃之类的东西
if you had a white square, like a white shit of glass or something
我不知道，就像这样，这是部分透明的，好了
I don't know, that was partially transparent, like this, okay
所以这就是混合的原理，如果你们有任何问题
so that's how blending works, if you have any questions
请在下面的评论区留言
leave them in the comments below
其实很简单
it is actually quite simple
一旦你们明白它是如何工作的
once you understand how it works
就可以做几个我在家里做过的例子
do a few of these examples that I've done at home
尝试一些不同的函数，尝试一些不同的等式
try some different functions, try some different equations
把它写在纸上，看看你们会得到什么
just do it on paper and see what you get
学习这些东西真的很重要
learning these things is really important
因为使用混合是有意义的
because using blending is something
你们会在一般的图形编程中使用一段时间
that you'll be using for a while in graphics programming in general
我知道最困难的事情是总是像
and I know that the hardest thing is always being like
什么是SRC_ALPHA，什么是ONE_MINUS_SRC_ALPHA
well what's SRC_ALPHA, what's ONE_MINUS_SRC_ALPHA
我刚听说
I'm just told
将其设置为我的混合函数，并保持不变
set that as my blend function and leave it as that
但是它是如何工作的呢
but how does it actually work
这就是它的工作原理，希望你们喜欢
well this is how it works, so I hope you enjoyed that
如果你们喜欢的话，可以点击这个喜欢按钮
if you did, you can hit the like button
也可以访问patreon.com/TheCherno来支持这个系列
it also helps support this series by going to patreon.com/TheCherno
像往常一样，非常感谢所有支持这个系列的人
huge thank you as always to all the people who are supporting this series
没有这些人，就不会有今天，非常感谢你们
it would not be here without those people, so huge thank you
说真的，每个人都应该感谢他们
everyone should be thanking them really
如果你们喜欢这个系列
if you are enjoying this series
希望你们喜欢这个ppt演示的风格
hope you enjoyed this little powerpoint presentation style
我其实挺喜欢的
I actually quite liked it
因为我不用整天挥舞双手
because instead of me waving my hands around all day
试着画图，试着把它形象化
and actually trying to draw things and try and visualize this
或者尝试现场绘制东西
or attempting to actually draw stuff live
我可以制作这些精致的小图表，淡入动画
I can just kind of make these cute little diagrams and fade in animations
我不知道，我的意思是，我个人认为这是一个非常酷的想法
and I don't know, I mean, I personally think it's a really cool idea
请在下面的评论区告诉我你们的想法
let me know what your thoughts are in the comment section below
下次我们将继续我们的渲染和所有这些
next time we're going to continue on with our render and all that
很酷的东西，现在我们有了混合，这是非常重要的
cool stuff, now that we have blending working, that's very important
在那之前，我们可以开始正确渲染纹理
and we can actually start rendering textures properly until then
下次见，拜
I'll see you next time, goodbye